Today I am going to teach you
سأعلّمكم اليوم كيفيّة
how to play my favorite game:
لعب لعبتي المفضّلة:
massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling.
مصارعة إبهام شديدة تعدّد اللاعبين.
It's the only game in the world that I know of
إنّها اللّعبة الوحيدة في العالم التي أعرفها
that allows you, the player,
و توفّر لك، أي اللّاعب،
the opportunity to experience
فرصة الاحساس
10 positive emotions in 60 seconds or less.
ب10 مشاعر إيجابية في أقلّ من 60 ثانية.
This is true, so if you play this game with me today
الأمر صحيح، إذن إن قمت بلعبها اليوم معي
for just one single minute,
لمدة لا تتجاوز الدقيقة الواحدة،
you will get to feel joy, relief, love, surprise,
فسوف تحسّ بالسعادة، الرّاحة، الحب، المفاجأة،
pride, curiosity, excitement, awe and wonder,
الفخر، الفضول، الحماس، الروعة و الاعجاب،
contentment, and creativity,
الرّضا و الإبداع،
all in the span of one minute.
كلّها على مدى دقيقة واحدة.
So this sounds pretty good, right? Now you're willing to play.
ألا يبدو الأمر جيدا جدا؟ الآن أنت ترغب في اللّعب.
In order to teach you this game,
حتّى أتمكّن من تعليمكم طريقة اللّعب،
I'm going to need some volunteers
سوف أحتاج بعض المتطوّعين
to come up onstage really quickly,
للصعود إلى الرّكح لمدة وجيزة،
and we're going to do a little hands-on demo.
و سوف نريكم من خلال تجربة صغيرة.
While they're coming up, I should let you know,
بينما هم قادمون، عليّ اخباركم
this game was invented 10 years ago
أنّ هذه اللعبة اخترعت من 10 سنوات مضت
by an artists' collective in Austria named Monochrom.
من قبل فنّان نمساويّ يدعى (مونوكروم).
So thank you, Monochrom.
لذلك شكرا لك (مونوكروم).
Okay, so most people are familiar
حسنا، معظم النّاس يعرفون كيفية حدوث
with traditional, two-person thumb-wrestling.
مصارعة الإبهام التقليدية.
Sunni, let's just remind them.
(ساني)، دعنا نقوم بتذكيرهم.
One, two, three, four, I declare a thumb war, and we wrestle,
واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة، أعلن حرب الإبهام، ثمّ نتصارع،
and of course Sunni beats me because she's the best.
و بالطبع تغلبني (ساني) لأنّها الأفضل.
Now the first thing about massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling,
أول ما يجب معرفته عن مصارعة إبهام شديدة تعدّد اللاعبين،
we're the gamer generation.
نحن ننتمي لجيل اللاّعبين،
There are a billion gamers on the planet now,
هناك قرابة مليار لاعب على الكوكب إلى حدّ الآن،
so we need more of a challenge.
لهذا فنحن نحتاج أمرا أكثر تحدّيا.
So the first thing we need is more thumbs.
أول ما نحتاجه هو عدد أكثر من الأصابع،
So Eric, come on over.
(إريك) اقترب قليلا.
So we could get three thumbs together,
حتّي نتمكن من جمع 3 أصابع معا،
and Peter could join us.
و بإمكان (بيتر) مشاركتنا.
We could even have four thumbs together,
باستطاعتنا جمع 4 أصابع معا،
and the way you win
أمّا من يربح فهو
is you're the first person to pin someone else's thumb.
أول شخص يقوم بتثبيت إبهام شخص آخر.
This is really important. You can't, like,
وهو أمر مهمّ فعلا، إذ ليس بامكانك
wait while they fight it out and then swoop in at the last minute.
الانتظار الآخرين بينما يتصارعون ثمّ تحرّك إبهامك في آخر لحظة.
That is not how you win.
تلك ليس طريقة الفوز.
Ah, who did that? Eric you did that.
من قام بذلك؟ أنت، (إريك).
So Eric would have won. He was the first person to pin my thumb.
إذا فهو الفائز. إنّه أول لاعب قام بتثبيت إبهامي.
Okay, so that's the first rule,
حسنا، كانت تلك القاعدة الاولى،
and we can see that three or four
3 أو 4 أشخاص هو في العادة
is kind of the typical number of thumbs in a node,
العدد المناسب لتشكيل عقدة،
but if you feel ambitious, you don't have to hold back.
لكن إن كنت طموحا، فلا تكمح طموحك.
We can really go for it.
تستطيع أن تبحث عن المزيد،
So you can see up here.
كما يمكنكم الرّؤية هنا.
Now the only other rule you need to remember is,
القاعدة الوحيدة التي عليك تذكّرها هي،
gamer generation, we like a challenge.
أنّنا نرغب في التّحدي.
I happen to notice you all have
لاحظت أنّكم جميعا تمتلكون
some thumbs you're not using.
إبهاما لا تستعملونه.
So I think we should kind of get some more involved.
لذا أظنّ أنّ عليكم المشاركة قليلا.
And if we had just four people,
إن كان هناك أربعة أشخاص بالضبط،
we would do it just like this,
بامكاننا القيام بهذا،
and we would try and wrestle
حيث كلّ منّا يحاول المصارعة
both thumbs at the same time.
باصبعيه الاثنين في نفس الوقت.
Perfect.
ممتاز.
Now, if we had more people in the room,
لو كان هناك أكثر عدد من الأشخاص بالغرفة،
instead of just wrestling in a closed node,
يمكننا تعويض المصارعة في عقد مغلقة
we might reach out and try and grab some other people.
بالمصارعة على مجال أوسع مع عدد أكثر من الأشخاص.
And in fact, that's what we're going to do right now.
و في الواقع، هذا تماما ما سنقوم به الآن.
We're going to try and get all, something like,
سوف نحاول جمع كلّ أصابع الإبهام
I don't know, 1,500 thumbs in this room
في هذه الغرفة، قرابة 1500 اصبعا
connected in a single node.
مرتبطة معا في عقدة واحدة.
And we have to connect both levels,
و علينا أن نربط بين الطابقين،
so if you're up there, you're going to be
لذا إن كنت في الأعلى فسوف تضطرّ
reaching down and reaching up.
للانحناء و محاولة الوصول إلى الاخرين.
Now — (Laughter) —
الآن — (ضحك) —
before we get started --
قبل البدأ --
This is great. You're excited to play. —
هذا رائع. أنتم متحمسون للّعب. —
before we get started, can I have the slides back up here really quick,
قبل البدأ، هل يمكنني استعادة الصّور هنا بسرعة،
because if you get good at this game,
لأنّكم إن برعتم في هذه اللّعبة،
I want you to know there are some advanced levels.
عليكم معرفة أنّ هناك مستويات أعلى.
So this is the kind of simple level, right?
إذن هذا هو المستوى الأقل بساطة، صح؟
But there are advanced configurations.
لكن هناك تطبيقات متطوّرة.
This is called the Death Star Configuration.
هذا مستوى "نجم الموت".
Any Star Wars fans?
هل من أحبّاء ل"حرب النّجوم"؟
And this one's called the Möbius Strip.
و هذه تدعى "شريط موبيوس".
Any science geeks, you get that one.
أحبّاء العلوم سيفهمون الأمر.
This is the hardest level. This is the extreme.
هذا أصعب مستوى. إنّه الأكثر شدّة.
So we'll stick with the normal one for now,
لذا سوف نتمسّك بالمستوى العاديّ الآن،
and I'm going to give you 30 seconds,
سأمنحكم 30 ثانية،
every thumb into the node,
لربط كلّ إبهام إلى العقدة،
connect the upper and the lower levels,
اربطوا بين الطابقين،
you guys go on down there.
أنتم تعالوا إلى هنا.
Thirty seconds. Into the network. Make the node.
30 ثانية. إلى الشّبكة. اصنعوا عقدة.
Stand up! It's easier if you stand up.
قفوا، الأمر أسهل إن وقفتم.
Everybody, up up up up up!
جميعكم، هيا قفوا.
Stand up, my friends.
قفوا يا أصدقائي.
All right.
حسنا.
Don't start wrestling yet.
لا تبدؤوا بالمصارعة بعد.
If you have a free thumb, wave it around,
إن كان لك إبهام حرّ، فابحث
make sure it gets connected.
عن طريقة لربطه بالشبكة.
Okay. We need to do a last-minute thumb check.
حسنا، نحتاج إلى التحقّق للمرة الأخيرة.
If you have a free thumb, wave it around to make sure.
إن كان لك إبهام حرّ، اربطه بالعقدة.
Grab that thumb!
امسك ذلك الإبهام!
Reach behind you. There you go.
إنّه وراءك، أحسنت.
Any other thumbs?
هل من أصابع متبقّية؟
Okay, on the count of three, you're going to go.
حسنا، تبدأ اللعبة عندي عدّي لثلاثة.
Try to keep track. Grab, grab, grab it.
حاولوا التّركيز. امسك، امسكه جيدا.
Okay? One, two, three, go!
حسنا؟ واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، ابدؤوا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Did you win? You got it? You got it? Excellent!
هل فزت؟ هل أجدت الأمر؟ ممتاز!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well done. Thank you. Thank you very much.
جيّد جدّا. شكرا لكم. شكرا جزيلا لكم.
All right.
حسنا.
While you are basking in the glow
بينما أنت سعيد
of having won your first
لكونك فزت في أوّل لعبة
massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling game,
مصارعة إبهام شديدة تعدّد اللاعبين،
let's do a quick recap on the positive emotions.
إذا لنتذكّر المشاعر الإيجابيّة.
So curiosity.
الفضوليّة.
I said "massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling."
عندما قلت، "مصارعة إبهام شديدة تعدّد اللاعبين".
You were like, "What the hell is she talking about?"
كنتم تتساءلون،"ما الذي تتحدّث عنه بحقّ الجحيم؟"
So I provoked a little curiosity.
لقد أثرت فضولكم.
Creativity: it took creativity to solve the problem
الإبداع: يطلّب الأمر إبداعا
of getting all the thumbs into the node.
لربط جميع الأصابع في العقدة.
I'm reaching around and I'm reaching up.
عليك البحث في كلّ الأماكن،
So you used creativity. That was great.
إذا لقد استعملتم الإبداع، هذا رائع.
How about surprise? The actual feeling
ماا عن المفاجأة؟ ما نحسّ به عند
of trying to wrestle two thumbs at once is pretty surprising.
محاولة مصارعة ابهامين في نفس الوقت مفاجئ جدّا.
You heard that sound go up in the room.
لقد سمعنا ذلك الصوت يعول في الغرفة.
We had excitement. As you started to wrestle,
كان هناك حماس. عند بدأ المصارعة،
maybe you're starting to win or this person's, like, really into it,
ربّما أنت نحو طريق الفوز أو أنّ الشخص بجانبك منغمس في اللّعب،
so you kind of get the excitement going.
وهو ما يحافظ على الحماس.
We have relief. You got to stand up.
هناك احساس بالراحة. لقد كان بوسعك الوقوف.
You've been sitting for awhile, so the physical relief,
لقد كنتم جالسين لمدة طويلة، لذا كان هناك راحة جسدية،
getting to shake it out.
فرصة تحريك جسدك.
We had joy. You were laughing, smiling. Look at your faces. This room is full of joy.
السعادة، لقد كنتم تضحكون، تبتسمون. انظروا إلى وجوهكم. هذه الغرفة مليئة بالسعادة.
We had some contentment.
كان هناك الرضا.
I didn't see anybody sending text messages or checking their email while we were playing,
لم أر أيّ منكم يبعث رسائل نصية قصيرة أو يتفقّد بريده الالتكرونيّ أثناء اللّعب،
so you were totally content to be playing.
كنّا قنوعين تماما باللّعب.
The most important three emotions,
الأحاسيس الثلاثة الأكثر أهميّة،
awe and wonder, we had everybody connected physically for a minute.
الروعة و الاعجاب، لقد اتّصل جميع الحاضرين هنا مع بعضهم البعض جسديا لمدة دقيقة.
When was the last time you were at TED
متى كانت آخر مرة أثناء حضورك لTED
and you got to connect physically with every single person in the room?
و تمكّنت فيها من التّواصل جسديّا مع كلّ الحاضرين بالغرفة؟
And it's truly awesome and wondrous.
وهو أمر فعلا رائع و مدهش.
And speaking of physical connection,
بمناسبة الحديث عن الاتّصال الجسدي،
you guys know I love the hormone oxytocin,
تعلمون أنّني أحبّ هرمون الأكسيتوسين،
you release oxytocin, you feel bonded to everyone in the room.
يقع إفراز الهرمون، و تحسّ بالارتباط مع الجميع بالغرفة.
You guys know that the best way to release oxytocin quickly
هل تعلمون أنّ أفضل طريقة لإفرار الأوكسيتوسين بطريقة سريعة
is to hold someone else's hand for at least six seconds.
هي الإمساك بيد شخص آخر مدة 6 ثوان على الأقلّ.
You guys were all holding hands for way more than six seconds,
و أنتم كنتم ممسكين أياد بعضكم لمدّة أطول بكثير من ذلك،
so we are all now biochemically primed
إذن فنحن الآن مستعدّون بيولوجيّا
to love each other. That is great.
لنحبّ بعضنا البعض. أمر رائع.
And the last emotion of pride.
و أخيرا احساس الفخر.
How many people are like me. Just admit it.
كم من شخص هنا مثلي، اعترفوا.
You lost both your thumbs.
إن خسرتم إبهاميكم.
It just didn't work out for you.
إن لم تجد القيام بالأمر،
That's okay, because you learned a new skill today.
لا بأس، لأنّك تعلّمت مهارة جديدة اليوم.
You learned, from scratch, a game you never knew before.
هل تعلّمت من الصفر لعبة لم تكن تعرفها مسبقا.
Now you know how to play it. You can teach other people.
الآن أنت تعرف كيفية لعبها. يمكنك تعليم غيرك.
So congratulations.
لذا، أهنّؤك.
How many of you won just won thumb?
كم منكم ربح بإبهام واحد؟
All right. I have very good news for you.
حسنا، لي أخبار جيدة جدا لكم.
According to the official rules
وفقا للقواعد الرّسمية
of massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling,
للعبة مصارعة الإبهام هذه،
this makes you a grandmaster of the game.
فإنّ ذلك يجعلك خبيرا باللّعبة.
Because there aren't that many people who know how to play,
لأنّ عددا قليلا جدّا من النّاس يعرفون كيفية اللّعب،
we have to kind of accelerate the program
لذا علينا الارتفاع بالمستوى
more than a game like chess.
أكثر من لعبة كالشّطرنج.
So congratulations, grandmasters.
تهانيّ أيّهما الخبراء.
Win one thumb once, you will become a grandmaster.
فز بإبهام واحد مرّة و ستصبح خبيرا.
Did anybody win both their thumbs?
هل من أحد فاز بإبهاميه الاثنين؟
Yes. Awesome. Okay.
نعم. رائع. حسنا،
Get ready to update your Twitter or Facebook status.
استعدّوا لتحديث منشوارتكم على الفايسبوك و التويتر.
You guys, according to the rules,
لأنّكم و حسب القواعد،
are legendary grandmasters, so congratulations.
تعتبرون خبراء أسطوريّين. أهنّؤكم.
I will just leave you with this tip, if you want to play again.
سوف أترككم مع هذه النّصيحة، في حال إن لعبتم مرّة أخرى.
The best way to become a legendary grandmaster,
أفضل طريقة كي تصبح خبيرا أسطوريّا،
you've got your two nodes going on.
هو لعب بعقدتين.
Pick off the one that looks easiest.
اختر الأسهل حيث
They're not paying attention. They look kind of weak.
خصومك غير منتبهين و يبدون ضعفاء.
Focus on that one and do something crazy
ركّز على تلك العقدة و قم بحركات مجنونة
with this arm.
بهذه اليد.
As soon as you win, suddenly stop.
و ما إن تربح، توقّف فجأة.
Everybody is thrown off. You go in for the kill.
فيتعب الجميع، و تكون تلك فرصتك.
That's how you become a legendary grandmaster of massively multiplayer thumb-wrestling.
بتلك الطريقة تصبح خبيرا في مصارعة الإبهام شديدة تعدّد اللاعبين.
Thank you for letting me teach you my favorite game.
شكرا للسماح لي بتعليمكم لعبتي المفضلة.
Wooo! (Applause)
وووووووو! (تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)